PROFESSOR: So we had depth-first search,
we had breadth-first search.
They operate in very different ways, but
none of them solve the problem of
what happens if the arcs in my
graph have different weights.
But actually, we have all the
machinery that we need.
So breadth-first search will, in a graph
like this, it's that same graph,
if there are weights on these, then
breadth-first search will find the
shortest path in terms of
the number of actions.
So for example, it's going to find this
path, which is expensive because
that short single arc in
fact, weighs nine.
OK, the shortest path might be something
that requires a little bit
more in terms of number of steps,
but less in terms of cost.
So let's figure out what we can do with
breadth-first search in order to
make it sensitive to the costs and do
the right thing in terms of returning
the cheapest rather than the
shallowest solution.
PROFESSOR: And the solution is
going to be something called
uniform cost search.
It's going to be more or less just
like breadth-first search.
You start at the top and
you work your way down.
The difference is rather than going
evenly across the layers, prioritizing
them by their depth, instead
we're going to prioritize
them by their cost.
So that cheap things get done first,
even if they are multiple
steps into the tree.
So let's see how it works here.
So the strategy is going to be
expand not a shallowest node,
but a cheapest node.
That means we need to keep track of
for every node that we put on the
fringe, we need to keep
track of its cost.
Now, its cost is the cumulative cost
all the way from the beginning.
So the beginning, the fringe
just contains the node s.
It has cost zero because we
haven't done anything.
And when we pop that off, we put
its successors onto the fringe.
So now the fringe contains d, e, and
p with their respective costs.
OK, I won't draw the fringe at all
times, but in this particular case, it
would actually look like s to d.
The costs here would be three.
S to e, the cost here would be nine.
And s to p, where the
cost would be one.
Now when we look at this fringe, the
thing we'll expand next is s to p
because it's cheapest, and
then we'll continue on.
So in this case we'll expand s to p.
Its child goes onto the fringe.
Its child in this case happens
to be expensive.
OK, what's the next cheapest
thing on the fringe?
It's d, so we expand that.
And now there are various successors
on the fringe.
The cheapest thing here, breadth-first
search would go for e up here.
It would go for the shallow one.
But the cheapest one is actually
over here. this path to b.
S to d to b.
And so we'll pop that.
And you can see that we are kind of
working our way down, but we're always
doing the cheapest thing next.
So next we pop off the
cost five path to e.
What's next?
The path to a.
OK, that has no children, so the next
thing is the cost seven path to r.
And then the path to f.
Now, here's an interesting thing.
We found the path to g, but we
don't declare victory yet.
And here it's critical that we don't.
So on the fringe is a bunch of
paths, including one to g.
We don't stop, and in particular we
don't even process the path to g
because it's not the cheapest.
Instead, what do we do?
We finally make our way back up here
to that shallow path to e.
We process that.
Now we've processed every path
in the tree up to cost nine.
What's next?
Next is the goal path.
We return it.
We declare victory.
And it actually turns out
that this process will
guarantee us the cheapest.
So I said it was like breadth-first
search.
What does that mean?
Well, you do all the kind of cost one
things, then the cost two things, then
the cost three things.
Breath-first search did the depth one
things, then the depth two things,
then the depth three things.
So the difference is although you're
moving from the top to the bottom,
you're doing it in this ragged way
that follows the cost contours.
At any given time, you will
have expanded all paths up
to a certain cost.
And that's going to trace some jagged
thing through the tree depending on
how uneven the costs are
in your search problem.
What are the properties
of this search?
Well, what nodes get expanded?
We already know.
First, we're going to expand everything
where the cost is, say,
less than or equal to 1.
Then, eventually we'll expand everything
less than or equal to 2.
Eventually, we'll expand everything with
costs less than or equal to 3.
And so what do we expand?
All nodes with cost less than the
cost of the cheapest solution.
OK.
All right.
Now we need some notation.
This is a little bit heavy handed.
If the solution costs C*--
so that's the cost of this thing
here, this thing costs C*--
all right, how deeply
could we have gone?
Well, it depends how far down in terms
of steps we could go because that's
going to tell us the branching
factor to what.
Well, if we can bound to the cost of an
individual action, so each action
cost at least epsilon, say, 0.1, then we
can look at C* divided by epsilon.
That's essentially how deep the cheapest
solution could be, right?
And in the worst case, we're going
to do everything in the
graph up to that step.
OK, so we could say, in the worst
case, this'll take time.
It's still exponential in b.
It's now b to this effective depth,
which is the cost of the solution--
so the more expensive the solution
the deeper you go--
and divided by the cost
of the cheapest arc.
So if the arcs are really cheap, you
might have to go really deep to get an
expensive solution.
OK, so it's kind of like breadth for
search, but that depth is harder to
think about.
How much space does the fringe take?
Well, just like depth first search, the
fringe is kind of the periphery,
and that means it's basically
the same cost.
It's still exponential.
Is this thing complete?
Basically like breadth-first search
again, assuming that the best solution
has a finite cost and the minimum arc
cost is positive, yes, this is
complete as well.
Now, for the kicker.
Is it optimal?
Well, I will state, but not
prove, that it's optimal.
I'll prove it next lecture, because
it'll be a special case of the A*
search algorithm.
So yes, this is an optimal method.
It will return not the shallowest
solution like breadth-first search,
but the cheapest according
to the weights.
What's it going to do?
Well remember, it explores increasing
cost contours, and the good of that is
it's complete and optimal.
The bad, which we're going to have to
fix next lecture, is that it explores
in every direction.
I'll show you that in the demo
and we'll fix it next time.
What that means is, from the start, you
consider all the things that you
could do that are cheap, whether they're
making progress towards the
goal or not.
Right.
So I want to get to that door, and
so I think of everything I
could do with 50 steps.
Probably that's a waste.
There's a lot of things you can do
with 50 steps that don't get you
anywhere to your door,
and we'll fix that.